but definitely if you're trying to help
someone in their life
uh do their yoga every day
try to help them find the yoga that fits
them and it might not be the one that
you're teaching
so it's a kind of
honesty
integrity to tell a student go try this
teacher go try that teacher you know
it means you're not attached to them
uh do you know david swenson
so he's the biggest tanga teacher he
taught me for a while and he i said
where's your studio he says i don't have
a studio
i'm like but you teach all over the
world your book has sold a half a
million copies
he's like i don't have a studio i don't
want a studio i said why he says
baseball cards
i said what do you mean baseball cards
he says people collect students like
baseball cards you know i've got
sting is my student and i've got
pavarotti as my student and you know
he subjects to this uh
you shouldn't try to possess the
students you see what i mean figure help
them figure out what's the best yoga for
them
and said maybe you go try ashtanga maybe
you go try onasara or you go cook
yourself in vikram
maybe you'll like it and then try to
bend heart yoga but be be honest and be
helpful say
try here's i like this ashtanga teacher
i don't like ishtanga myself but maybe
it's good for you you know i get angry
when i do ashtanga i don't know why
but other people i know they love it
they don't like any other kind of yoga
so you don't have to be like
what do you call
the party you know your party
communist party or you know
help them find the best match for them
that's your job as a teacher maybe it
won't be at your studio
but
for every student you send
to meet their dream teacher
you'll get three more trust me
karmically
it's the best way to get a lot of
students if you want a lot of students
the best way is to help them find the
teacher that they relate to you see what
i mean even if it's not you
because that proves that you're really
interested in their welfare
and you're not just interested in their
money or their time or their attention
right
and that's a very beautiful thing so
sometimes
encourage them to go to other studios
okay like i'm not going to teach you
headstand
i don't have time
i'm just here for three days for the
business seminar
here's the addresses of three studios
around you i like this one maybe you
like the other one
but go ask them to teach your head stuff
okay like that
help them find their own match
then they'll go every day okay like that
don't be attached to them
help them that's
teacher's job is not to glam on the
student it's to help them
okay uh
page nine at the bottom not so local
studio
that's a story about you know
whenever you travel
i i mean i
i guess some people don't travel all
their life but i do and
go go to yoga somewhere okay go find a
yoga class somewhere go to a spa
i have there's a spa in sedona called
los abregados
they have a sunday class it's not
advertised anywhere you can't go
tomorrow
but
after that you can
but you know i find these weird classes
and i find good teachers and
find just go to go to yoga somewhere
okay tell your students
go go to yoga wherever you are
you go to a trip to phoenix or you go to
trip to tokyo
take a class look it up online take a
class
and you learn so much right and you find
beautiful teachers all around the world
you learn new things everywhere we've
gone to i don't know
hundreds of classes
and we always learn something new and
it's fun you know and you meet new
people and
it's nice you get to lay down in the
dark with more total strangers
okay
okay page 10 dvd i like dvds
i'm not motivated enough to
push myself every day
you know i will always find some excuse
that
i even one day i got on the mat and i
still didn't do yoga
uh that's an achievement but uh
you know i changed and i got on the
mountain
so what i've been doing the last year or
so i buy dvds yoga dvds even my own
uh
and i
and i do yoga along with the dvd and
then somehow i have this thing in me
that i can't say no to a teacher
if if if the dvd teacher tells me to do
a headstand i'll do it
you know what i mean and
i promised myself i won't turn off the
dvd until it's over
because you can do that too you can just
shut them up
so i just found it really really helps
me and when we travel in a group
we we're in hotel rooms we're in little
hotel rooms we stack all the furniture
on the bed we get like 10 people in the
hotel room and we put on a dvd
and it's fun it's really fun so try it
okay i made you a list of dvds that i
like
uh
i haven't explored the whole field i
don't know all the dvds in the universe
but these are some that i these are some
that i like okay
page 11.
i like all the ysi dvds they're very
well done i like mirashani's dvds
which i do a lot i like geshe michael's
lady naguma dvd i don't know why
uh
jiva mukti has a 12 box set i really
like it it's a 12 set
box
and it's grouped by theme
so
one is called you know inversions one is
called back bending one is called
balancing
one is called yoga for busy people
and the outside of the dvd says 45
minutes and it's an hour and 10 minutes
that's that's true uh
rodney yee he used to be a ballet dancer
he's a chinese guy i always thought he
was just this pretty boy
but i i played a dvd and it's fantastic
and i really like his dvds
some of them are too easy okay so don't
do the
weight loss for
you know
elderly mothers or so you know like do
do whatever he says is super hard yoga
that's going to be a normal class so
you can buy them at barnes noble's okay
gaia gaia i like he's a really good
teacher i haven't never taken a class
from him personally but
i really enjoy his classes
janet stone is from san francisco i
don't know her from anybody
what's his name
kent gave me
he said my yoga teacher wanted me to
give you these dvds and i'm like
i have a stack of those dvds that people
gave me and would actually put it on one
day and it's great
hers are very good
so they're sort of
semi-challenging
but not crazy you want crazy you go to
anna forest
it's called five day intense of course
each class is two hours long you will
die before you finish an hour
if you don't crack your head open
so if you're into that
now like if you have to teach a
a big yoga program in a week
do the five-day thing it's two hours of
class
and it's hard and then you're all what
do you call it
buff when you come out i find this
cheese buff okay um
sean corn is this basic uh
ashtanga type vinyasa and i don't know
there's probably thousands of others i i
haven't got to them all yet okay
but what i'm saying is start your
collection start a collection i i buy
the dvd
i throw out the cover
i keep them in a little carry case and i
take it with me i tried to import them
into itunes it shuffles to asanas
uh so i'm just warning you don't try
uh
it gets really weird
i like to do we like to do
uh ningbo and mercedes and i we travel a
lot
and they're my assistants and luckily
they're partners so uh
and then we do yoga in the gate at the
airport you know you always have to sit
there for 45 minutes or something we
always do yoga at the gate so you like
you're in a rush
you're getting ready for the flight you
can't do your yoga
we take the yoga mat through the
security
we find an empty spot and we do yoga and
it inspires people like we did it in
mexico
where was that at vallarta puerto
vallarta
the day the class ended we all were in
the airport i think there were 40 of us
doing yoga on the floor
and it was so cool
and then on some longer flights i've had
people wander over and start doing yoga
with me
or you're in like vietnam and people are
staring at you and then they start
trying to do what you're doing and
maybe you turn on somebody like don't be
shy okay i was in colombia
in the in the
airport and
i just started doing yoga and all the
guards were trying to do it
you know so just do it you feel shy for
like two minutes people stare at you for
10 minutes and then life goes on
and maybe maybe they change maybe it
changes their life okay
uh
practicing with a friend is a good idea
if they're not the kind of friend who
will talk you out of doing yoga once
they get to your house
so
i find it much easier to do yoga with a
friend you know so like i say we we
travel we're leaving tomorrow for a long
tour
and we do yoga we always do yoga
together and the staff
the dci staff maybe there's 10 or 20 of
us
we always do our yoga even even if we're
doing a retreat
for a couple hundred business people we
set aside our yoga time
we teach them yoga
and then we go do our yoga be careful of
yoga teacher's disease
yoga teacher's disease is
you teach yoga and then you don't do
your yoga
okay and you gotta set aside time so
that's what we do on the and we have a
really good time we rotate so the staff
somebody on the staff one of the 10
people teaches every day
and we do our yoga together and you know
ningbo wants us to do
ohio state football things and
martial art things and we just do it
and it's a lot of fun
uh so we teach each other
we have a class uh yoga dates this is
our my new thing this is my new big
thing
so you know we usually go out
we
some crazy people have moved to arizona
we like to spend time together
so we used to go like to dinner and then
we'd go to hell see a movie right and
then one day somebody said hey let's go
do yoga together at this studio before
we go to dinner you know and then we're
like oh yeah okay let's try
and now it's like the hottest thing you
know
we have a date we have yoga dates and
like last time there were 14 people
came on the yoga date
and
first we have a tibetan class
he does some ancient logic text
for an hour and a half or she does her
sutra she's doing she's translating a
sutra
and we have a tibetan class then we go
to yoga together like 15 people
and we just crash the class we actually
pay
and and where what do you mean
we're off the effects of the yoga
and then then maybe we go to a movie
but it's like a really like try to think
of uh
taking your friends out for yoga and
it's really fun it's really really fun
like just getting to have it like once a
week
we try like once a week when we're in in
arizona
which is once every three months
and we go out for a yoga date together
like and it's a lot of fun we went to
urban yoga
was it urban yeah
yeah we had a good class down there and
then we go to
what's in anton's classes or if we're in
tucson we go to darren's classes yeah
it's really fun
just do it with a bunch of people call
them out and say let's go out for yoga
do it
and it's healthy and it's it's positive
and it's
it's
constructive uh instead of you know
going out and having wine and pizza or
something like that
uh
teaching elderly people is a good thing
to do
if you're having trouble doing your own
yoga teach teach a class for somebody
else
and then do the yoga while you're
teaching right
page 13 be an example okay you can't
talk your students into the importance
of a daily yoga practice if you're
obviously not doing it okay
i'll tell you after many years of
teaching i've been teaching for i don't
know almost 40 years
people don't do what you say they watch
you and they do what you do
okay that's
just like kids
you know that you can tell your kids
anything you're you're a parent
and you can sit there and lecture your
kids all day
in the end they'll do whatever you do
you know and the same with dharma
students or yoga students
you can keep telling them how important
it is to do a daily practice but if
you're obviously not doing it then they
won't do it okay so the best way
to get other people to do a daily
practice is
to do your own practice and then people
will see you're all strong and healthy
and happy
then they'll say i want to be like i
want to be like her
uh
to me your job as a teacher
you
we have all these lesser motivations for
teaching all of us anybody i do too we
all do they wear off after 30 or 40
years okay
but it takes about that much time
uh you want attention
uh you want people to tell you how good
you look you know
maybe you want people's money
maybe you want sexual attention maybe
you want
all kinds of things you know maybe you
want to control people
maybe you enjoy that maybe you're
insecure and you want to
like control